Hello. Today's דף daf is ג, gimmel, three, and we are continuing
in חגיגה. Chagigah. And the immediate discussion here has been
what is the story of the חרש cheresh that is exempt from
from ראיה, re'iyah, from being עולה לרגל. oleh leregel. Before we continue
and I don't know whether רב חגי Rav Chagai touched on this
or not, but I'll just mention very briefly.
The first תוספות Tosafot discusses, you know, this issue about חייב בראיה,
chayav bire'iyah, points out that the simple that throughout the entire מסכת
masekhet and entire discussion ראיה re'iyah means the קרבן ראיה, korban re'iyah,
the עולת ראיה, olat re'iyah, the קרבן korban that is brought. But
he points out that רש״י Rashi says the מצוה mitzvah to appear,
is it distinct from actually לראות בעזרה? lerei'ot ba'azarah? You have to
just appear in the עזרה. azarah. Is that a distinct מצוה mitzvah
from bringing the עולת ראיה? olat re'iyah? And he points to a
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that actually says that while it's only the males and
everybody listed in this משנה mishna that is obligated in the עולת
ראיה olat re'iyah and not and not, you know, and everybody that's
excluded is excluded, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that the מצוה mitzvah to
appear in the עזרה, azarah, to literally be עולה לרגל, oleh leregel,
applies to everyone, even women, children, learns it out from הקהל. hakhel.
So it's a fascinating idea, an idea that the תורה Torah says
is once every seven years, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says actually applies to
everybody is supposed to be עולה לרגל, oleh leregel,
and then תוספות Tosafot goes on to prove that that clearly is
not the position of the בבלי. Bavli. Okay, but it's interesting to
just note, you know, that that fact that they're they're distinguishing between
how we tend to focus it very concretely on the קרבן, korban,
as opposed to thinking just more broadly of this issue of being
עולה לרגל. oleh leregel. Okay, so I just wanted to just make
sure that that point was clear. All right, so now what we
do is, and also make maybe make one other brief point from
the דף daf yesterday, which is the דרשה drasha about being able
to have sight in both eyes, כשם שבאים לראות כך באים ליראות,
keshem sheba'im lirot kach ba'im lera'ot, the same way they come to
see, they're there to be seen, as if they're at parties to
see and to be seen, right? So anyway, no,
anyway, so and it says the same way God sees with two
eyes, you have to be seen you have to see with two
eyes, which of course is ironic, right? God sees with two eyes,
I mean the anthropomorphism there shown. But besides that, the important point
to mention is, is that a דרשה drasha of, you know, we
might even be given to think having read that דרשה drasha that
it's okay, the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is you come
to be seen, but we're also reading it as you come to
see, and we're equating the two. But it is worth pointing out
that the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is actually you come
to see God, and it says שלוש פעמים בשנה יראה כל זכורך
את פני. shalosh pe'amim bashanah yera'eh kol zekhurkha et pnei. So יראה
yera'eh means you will be seen. But the problem with that as
the grammar is the word את. et. שלוש פעמים בשנה יראה כל
זכורך את פני. shalosh pe'amim bashanah yera'eh kol zekhurkha et pnei. את
et describes the object of the verb. So so to be seen
by God is יראה לפני. yera'eh lifnei. Okay, יראה את yera'eh et
doesn't work. The real and there's no נקודות. nekudot. So clearly the
פשט pshat way of reading that פסוק pasuk is שלוש פעמים בשנה
יראה כל זכורך את פני. shalosh pe'amim bashanah yir'eh kol zekhurkha et
pnei. You will see God when you come up to the רגל,
regel, right? But that's very very anthropomorphic. So you know we read
it יראה. yera'eh. But this דרשה drasha of כשם
שבאים לראות כך באים ליראות keshem sheba'im lirot kach ba'im lera'ot or
כך באים לראות kach ba'im lirot whichever way you read it, anyway,
really sort of raises up both of the meanings of that word
and it is important to notice, you know, again particularly as it
emerges from that דרשה drasha of the two eyes, you know, that
this is we spoke about appearing before being seen in the עזרה,
azarah, but there is a real sense in the פשט pshat of
the פסוק, pasuk, very anthropomorphic sense, of coming and seeing, directly encountering
and seeing God.
How about the את et there is like a with? Like you
will be seen with God?
Oh, so who are you seen with? It's important. Yeah, you're not
forced to have it be a direct object indicator.
It could mean with, but they choose to read it that way
for the דרשה. drasha. Maybe,
maybe.
I still would question whether that's פשט. pshat. It seems to me,
not just me, a lot of scholars, that the simple פשט pshat
is to see. Okay, anyway, let's move but that's an interesting one.
Let's move on now. So now we are going to pick up,
so that's about seeing, and now we pick up about hearing.
Let's just pick up quickly, I know that what was covered yesterday,
but I'm just going to read it very quickly from the two
dots on ב עמוד ב, bet amud bet, just so we get
the flow. מדבר ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר חייב. medaber ve'eino shome'a
shome'a ve'eino medaber chayav. If one speaks and can't hear, or hears
and cannot speak, is obligated. So the גמרא gemara says והתניא ve'hatanya
מדבר ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר פטור medaber ve'eino shome'a shome'a ve'eino
medaber patur that actually if one can only speak or only hear
but not the other you're exempt. Okay, after he's established that the
classic חרש, Cheresh, the classic person who is fully exempt from מצוות
Mitzvot is the one who both cannot speak and cannot hear, and
therefore logically by the way the משנה Mishnah did not say מדבר
ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר חייב. Medaber ve'eino shome'a shome'a ve'eino medaber
chayav. That was the inference that the גמרא Gemara made, having interpreted
the word חרש Cheresh to be both deaf and mute. Having interpreted
it that way, the inference was if one is only deaf or
only mute one is חייב Chayav and now the גמרא Gemara is
playing out that inference. I should by the way make a point
about that as well which is, and this will get expanded in
חגיגה Chagigah this whole status of חרש. Cheresh. For a very long
time I assumed when you hear about the way חרש Cheresh is
considered not obligated and fundamentally not a בר חיובא, Bar chiyuva, I
figured okay, how many people are both deaf and mute? Like that's
rare, somebody doesn't have the ability of speaking together with not the
ability of hearing, but then I realized that actually for the גמרא
Gemara pretty much anybody who was deaf was a deaf-mute because the
inability to articulate in a way that is comprehensible, because deaf people
if they're born deaf being able to get that audio feedback and
to
modulate and to speak in a way that's
comprehensible, was not really been possible. I mean obviously today we have
different situations. But anyway so for the גמרא Gemara it's important to
note that almost everybody who was deaf or certainly was born deaf
was a deaf-mute. The person that was not a deaf-mute was the
person that learned to speak and was not born deaf and then
became deaf later. So it really becomes a very large category and
that's lead to a lot of very important halakhic discussion, especially when
schools for the deaf were developed and the deaf were able to
actually, it became clear that the deaf were intelligent and they were
able to communicate and sign language and all the assumptions that had
been made about their intelligence and ability were shown to be wrong
and that's a whole fascinating story in itself about that halakhic development
around that. But that's important to realize that the standard deaf person
born deaf is considered deaf-mute. But here then we have if it's
only one or the other, okay somebody was born with hearing and
then became deaf, then the implication of the משנה Mishnah is חייב.
Chayav. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to work that out.
והתניא: Ve'atanya: Is that true? Didn't we teach in a ברייתא Baraita
מדבר ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר פטור? Medaber ve'eino shome'a shome'a ve'eino
medaber patur? So even missing one of those senses is exempt. So
אמר רבינא ואי תימא רבא: Amar Ravina ve'iteima Rava: חסורי מחסרא והכי
קתני. Chisura mechsara vehachi katani.
No, it's missing some words and here's how it should be read,
which is a real question whether it means whether the גמרא Gemara
is really editing the text or just telling you that this is
the context you have to read into, the implicit assumptions you have
to read into it. והכי קתני, Vehachi katani, but either way here's
what it means to say: הכל חייבין בראיה ובשמחה חוץ מחרש המדבר
ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר שפטור מן הראיה. Hakol chayavin bire'iyah uvesimcha
chutz micheresh hamedaber ve'eino shome'a shome'a ve'eino medaber shepatur min hare'iyah.
Everybody is obligated in שמחה Simcha bringing the שלמי שמחה, Shalmei simcha,
another קרבן Korban that's brought on the רגל Regal ושמחת Vesamachta
and the
קרבן ראייה Korban re'iyah except for a חרש Cheresh who is מדבר
ואינו שומע שומע ואינו מדבר, Medaber ve'eino shome'a shome'a ve'eino medaber, somebody
who's missing one of these senses is exempt from ראייה. Re'iyah. ואף
על פי שפטור מן הראיה חייב בשמחה. Ve'af al pi shepatur min
hare'iyah chayav besimcha. So then and those people, the one who either
cannot hear or cannot speak, is exempt from ראייה Re'iyah as we
know ראייה Re'iyah we've already seen has much more many more criteria,
but is still obligated in the מצווה Mitzvah of bringing a שלמי
שמחה. Shalmei simcha. Why? Because such a person is obligated is a
בר חיובא. Bar chiyuva. So whatever this problem is of not having
one of the senses, that's only an exception from the מצווה Mitzvah
of ראייה, Re'iyah, but general מצוות Mitzvot obligated and therefore obligated in
שמחה. Simcha. Now then as the משנה Mishnah continues and talks about
a חרש Cheresh which the implication is a full חרש, Cheresh, ושאינו
לא שומע ולא מדבר, Veshe'eino lo shome'a velo medaber, somebody who both
cannot hear and cannot speak, a full חרש, Cheresh, ושוטה וקטן פטור
אף מן השמחה. Veshoteh vekatan patur af min hasimcha. But when talking
about a full חרש Cheresh like a חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh shoteh
vekatan, that classic type
of that group, that three part group of חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh
shoteh vekatan, which is the חרש Cheresh that is not obligated at
all, then like the שוטה וקטן Shoteh vekatan they're fully exempt and
they're exempt even from שמחה. Simcha. הוא פטור מכל מצוות האמורות בתורה
Hu patur mikol mitzvot hamurot batorah since they're exempt from all the
מצוות. Mitzvot. So basically it's the גמרא's Gemara way of saying that
חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh shoteh vekatan when you get that grouping means
a full חרש Cheresh who is completely exempt from מצוות Mitzvot and
from all מצוות. Mitzvot. It's not a limited exemption from עולת ראייה
Olat re'iyah which even has more criteria. So while it's true that
from עולת ראייה Olat re'iyah even a partial חרש Cheresh is exempt,
the חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh shoteh vekatan that's mentioned as the group,
that's the full חרש Cheresh and the people in that group would
be exempt not just from עולת ראייה, Olat re'iyah, would be exempt
from all מצוות, Mitzvot, all קרבנות Korbanot and so on. Okay, but
now we are basically trying to say that the משנה Mishnah would
also exclude a partial חרש Cheresh and now we have to figure
out why that would be. What makes that person specially excluded from
the מצווה Mitzvah of עולת ראייה? Olat re'iyah? תניא... Tanya... תניא נמי
הכי *Tanya nami hachi*, הכל חייבים בראייה ובשמחה חוץ מחרש המדבר ואינו
שומע שומע ואינו מדבר שפטורין מן הראייה *Hakol chayavim bire'iyah ubesimchah chutz
mecheresh hamedaber ve'eino shome'a, shome'a ve'eino medaber, shepturin min hare'iyah*. So everybody's
obligated in all מצוות *mitzvot* except for a חרש *cheresh* that can
speak and not hear or hear and not speak, that is missing
one of the senses, that in that type of a case, missing
one of the senses is enough to exclude somebody from עולת ראייה
olass re-iyah *Olat Ri'ah*, and even though they're excluded from the עולת
ראייה olas re'iyah. *Olat Ri'ah* which is a very, like we said,
which has more criteria, חייב chayav בשמחה *chayav besimchah*, but that person
fundamentally is obligated in all מצוות *mitzvot* in the התורה *haTorah*. It's
just a special exception from
עולת ראייה olas re'iyah *Olat Ri'ah*. But now there's another group of
people that's fully exempt from all the מצוות *mitzvot*. Somebody that can
neither speak or hear, a full חרש *cheresh*, חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh
shoteh vekatan*, or a שוטה *shoteh* or a קטן *katan*, and those
people that are fully exempt, פטור מן השמחה *patur min hasimchah*, even
exempt from the שמחה *simchah*, פטור מכל מצוות האמורות בתורה *patur mikol
mitzvot ha'amurot batorah*. Okay, so again, you have חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh
shoteh vekatan* which is the full חרש *cheresh*, but our משנה Mishna,
*Mishnah* mostly our משנה's Mishnah, *Mishnah's* interest is to exclude people that
are not generally excluded from מצוות *mitzvot*. Our משנה's Mishnah, *Mishnah's* interest
is to exclude people that have a special exemption from the מצווה
*mitzvah* of עולת ראייה *Olat Ri'ah*. So what we're trying to do
is force into the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* an idea that in addition
to the חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh vekatan* group where the חרש
*cheresh* is the full חרש *cheresh*, which is a general exemption, we
also have a special exemption from עולת ראייה *Olat Ri'ah* which is
somebody that's even a partial חרש *cheresh*. And now we have to
understand why that is. And this is somewhat similar to this idea
about being blind in one eye. Having full senses in order to
be able to be there, even if one is fundamentally obligated, we
already saw the issue about being blind in one eye, and now
we're going to see this issue about either not hearing or not
speaking. So let's take a look at what this is based on.
So now, three lines from the top, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: מאי שנא לעניין ראייה דפטירי *Mai shena le'inyan re'iyah
deptiri*, why is it different when it comes to the מצווה *mitzvah*
of the עולת ראייה *Olat Ri'ah* that they're exempt, what's the special
exemption there based on? ומאי שנא לעניין שמחה דמיחייבי בה *Umai shena
le'inyan simchah demichayvi bah*, and when it comes to a קרבן korban,
שמחה *Korban Simchah* they're obligated, they're obligated in all מצוות *mitzvot*. So
what is the special exemption of עולת ראייה *Olat Ri'ah*? לעניין ראייה
גמר ראייה ראייה מהקהל *Le'inyan re'iyah gamar re'iyah re'iyah mehak'hel*. Ah,
we learn it out from הקהל Hakhel *Hak'hel*, which is a funny
place to learn it out from because as I've indicated to you
as already הקהל's Hakhel *Hak'hel's* a very inclusive מצווה *mitzvah*, האנשים והנשים
והטף *ha'anashim vehanashim vehataf*, and so on. So we don't learn everything
out from הקהל Hakhel. *Hak'hel*, we don't learn to obligate women, but
we're going to learn this exemption from הקהל Hakhel *Hak'hel*. דכתיב *Dechtiv*,
as it says there, הקהל את העם האנשים והנשים והטף Hakhel et
ha'am ha'anashim v'hanashim v'hataf. *Hak'hel et ha'am ha'anashim vehanashim vehataf*, men, women,
and children. וכתיב בבוא כל ישראל Yisrael, לראות *Uchtiv bevo kol Yisrael
lera'ot*, and when all the people come to see. So there's a
גזירה שוה *gezerah shavah*, right? יראה כל זכורך בבוא כל ישראל Yisrael.
לראות *Yera'eh kol zechurecha bevo kol Yisrael lera'ot*. והתם מנלן
*Vehatam minalan*, and how do you know that somebody who is mute
or deaf is exempt from הקהל Hakhel, *Hak'hel*? דכתיב למען ישמעו lema'an
yishme'u. ולמען ילמדו *dechtiv lema'an yishme'u ulema'an yilmedu*, they hear the reading
of the התורה *haTorah* in order that they should hear and in
order that they should learn. דתניא d'tanya, למען ישמעו lema'an yishme'u? פרט
למדבר ואינו שומע *Datanya lema'an yishme'u perat lemedaber ve'eino shome'a*, to hear,
it excludes somebody who is deaf even if somebody can speak and
they're considered a בר חיובא *bar chiyuva* and all that they've and
they've just become deaf later and so on. Nevertheless, by הקהל Hakhel,
*Hak'hel* the importance is to hear the reading of the התורה *haTorah*.
So if you can't hear, you're exempt, פרט למדבר ואינו שומע *perat
lemedaber ve'eino shome'a*. Now how do you exclude somebody who is mute?
ולמען ילמדו
*ulema'an yilmedu*, in order to learn, פרט לשומע ואינו מדבר *perat leshome'a
ve'eino medaber*. Somebody who can hear and not speak. Now that's a
funny exemption. Somebody can hear and not speak they can't learn? It's
one thing to say the חז"ל *Chazal* assumed that somebody who is
a חרש שוטה *cheresh shoteh*, doesn't have intellect because they couldn't understand
the person and so on and maybe they figured if you can't
take anything in, how much are you able to absorb? Like how
much are you able to learn? Whatever, I'm not saying that's not
what we think nowadays obviously, we know better, but you can understand
what that assumption is. But how could you assume that just because
somebody can't speak they can't learn? What's preventing them from learning just
because they can't speak? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* immediately questions this.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: למימרא דכי לא משתעי לא גמר
*Lemeimra dechi lo mishta'ei lo gamar*, do you mean to say that
somebody who can't speak can't learn, can't know, can't absorb knowledge? והא
הנהו תרי אלמי דהוו בשיבבותיה דרבי בני ברתיה דרבי יוחנן בן גודגדא
*Veha hanhu terei almei dehavu beshivvuteh deRabbi bnei barteh deRabbi Yochanan ben
Gudgada*, and now fascinating that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has sort of
like a
empirical evidence against
this, ואמרי לה בני אחתיה דרבי יוחנן *ve'amri lah bnei achateh
deRabbi Yochanan*, there were two mute people that were in the neighborhood
of רבי Rebbi *Rabbi*, the son of the the grandson, the son
of the daughter of רבי Rebbi, יוחנן בן גודגדא *Rabbi Yochanan ben
Gudgada*, and some say the son of his sister, the sister of
רבי Rebbe, יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. Anyway, there were these two mute people.
דכל אימת דהוה עייל רבי Rebbe לבי מדרשא הוו עיילי ויתבי קמיה
*Dechol eimat dehavah ayyel Rabbi levei midrasha havu ayyli veyatvi kameih*, that
whenever רבי Rebbe, *Rabbi* would come into the בית מדרש Beit Midrash
*Beit Midrash* they would come and they'd sit in front of him,
ומניידי ברישייהו *umenaydi beReisheihu*, and they would nod their heads, indicating that
they were understanding,
ומרחשין שפוותייהו *umerachashin sifevateihu*, and their lips would be
moving. ובעו so they clearly wanted to be able to talk about
what they were to speak, ובעי רבי רחמי עלייהו u-ba'ei Rebbi rachamei
aleihu and רבי Rebbe, prayed for them, ואיתסו ve-itissu and they were
healed. ואשתכח דהוו גמירי ve-ishtakach de-havu gemirei and now that they could
speak, it turned out that you talked with them and you found
out that they knew הלכתא וספרא וסיפרי וכולא ש"ס. hilchosa ve-sifra ve-sifrei
ve-chulla Shas. They knew הלכות halachos like and the ספרא, Sifra, the
מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha and all of the ששה סדרים. shisha sedarim.
Now there's not גמרא Gemara yet, it was the time of רבי,
Rebbe, but okay, it was all of all משנה, Mishnah they knew
all of תורה שבעל פה. Torah She-be'al Peh. Right.
So you see, there we go. So anyway, you see that somebody
can be mute and could have their full mental capacities and be
able to learn. So, אמר מר זוטרא קרי ביה למען ילמדו. amar
Mar Zutra krei beih lema'an yilmedu. Alright fine. פשט pshat is would
not exclude them, that somebody who's mute can learn. But somebody who's
mute says the גמרא Gemara can't teach, like again in an oral
culture and in a culture in which you have not developed sign
language,
so the גמרא Gemara felt that the full sense of teaching is
not possible without
speech. And therefore that's why they're exempt because of the דרשה drasha
on the פסוק pasuk is not just to learn but it's also
to be able to teach, to teach over. And that's learned from
הקהל Hakhel and therefore like applied here. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, רב
אשי אמר ודאי למען ילמדו הוא. Rav Ashi amar vadai lema'an yilmedu
hu. Look, internally I can prove without your whole discussion about these
people in רבי'ס Rebbi's community that the דרשה drasha of that about
to exclude a mute person, that it meant it was reading the
verse in order to teach, not just in order to learn. דאי
סלקא דעתך למען ילמדו, de-ei salka dachtech lema'an yilmedu, if it was
reading the verse just in order to learn and somehow it assumed
that because somebody was mute they couldn't
learn, so דכיון דלא משתעי לא גמרי de-keivan de-lo mishtayyei lo gamrei
if that was the assumption, like what we wind up rejecting, but
if the assumption was that we were saying it's about learning and
maybe because they can't speak they can't learn, that could not have
been the read of the ברייתא. braisa. Why?
דכיון דלא שמעי לא גמרי de-keivan de-lo sham'ei lo gamrei because then
it would also be assuming that if you can't hear you can't
learn. So האי מלמען ישמעו נפקא, hai mi-lema'an yishme'u nafka, so you
could have already got that out from למען ישמעו. lema'an yishme'u. Meaning
if the גמרא Gemara assumed that למען ילמדו lema'an yilmedu means you're
not able to learn, not you're not able to teach, and it
made the assumption that somebody mute couldn't learn, it certainly along with
that should have been assuming that somebody who's deaf can't learn, that
you can't even get the information in. So why did you need
to also have the פסוק pasuk of למען ישמעו? למען ילמדו, lema'an
yilmedu, if you had made those assumptions about people's inability to learn
because they're either mute or deaf, then you could have excluded both
of them from למען ילמדו. lema'an yilmedu. Since you did not, clearly
you're not assuming that these people can't learn, and you're therefore not
reading the verse as למען ילמדו lema'an yilmedu and you're not excluding
them based on למען ילמדו. lema'an yilmedu. So if you're excluding based
on למען ילמדו lema'an yilmedu it's only because you're reading it as
למען ילמדו lema'an yilmedu in order to teach. אלא ודאי למען ילמדו
הוא. ela vadai lema'an yilmedu hu. One minute. So אלא ודאי למען
ילמדו הוא. ela vadai lema'an yilmedu hu. So certainly you must be
reading the verse of למען ילמדו lema'an yilmedu and that would explain
and you're not making assumptions that these people cannot learn, but you're
excluding them because either they cannot hear or because they cannot teach.
So I have to say one second that it is like look,
in general these exclusions here are like troubling, that the sense of
people with even some types of imperfections are being excluded,
beyond the sort of normal hierarchy that we have of כהן ישראל,
Kohen, Yisrael, etc. which plays out certainly in the בית המקדש Beis
Ha-Mikdash and male and female just playing out here about the fact
that it's only ליראות כל זכורך, leira'os kol zechurcha, right, you're increasing
all of the degrees of exclusion that are going on here, in
terms
of not having sight in one eye, although that was debated, not
having this faculty, that faculty, and it's one part, it's one issue
by הקהל Hakhel, if you want to emphasize the idea, you're going
to absorb the experience, to learn it, maybe even to pass it
down and to teach it. So, okay, maybe you can sort of
understand that, although let's not forget that the גמרא Gemara said before,
it was yesterday, oh no, it's going to come back actually at
the end of today's דף, daf, not yesterday's דף, daf, why are
the infants coming? Right? So maybe there's a sense of gathering even
though you can't fully absorb, there's a just sense of being present.
But okay, איך שיהיה, eich she-yiheyeh, we could understand maybe the importance
of that by הקהל. Hakhel It's not so clear why these should
be like
exclusions by the עולת ראייה which clearly seems to be much more
about experiential, being present, experiential, not necessarily listening or hearing or so
on. So it's hard to understand exactly why we're having these exclusions
and again we're going to see even by הקהל Hakhel, we include
infants who aren't learning and aren't hearing and aren't teaching over. So
it's definitely a little bit challenging on the other hand nobody is
saying that these people can't come to the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash
and bring a קרבן, it's just saying that they're not obligated. So
they're not really being excluded from entering, they're just being sort of
exempt from
obligation. No.
No. Give me why did it start with it? Why didn't it
just say דכתיב בבוא כל ישראל לראות? dikhsiv b'vo kol yisrael leraos?
I don't know. I don't know. Unless it just wanted to introduce
that we're talking about הקהל, Hakhel so it said מהקהל דכתיב הקהל,
me-Hakhel dikhsiv Hakhel, but I don't know, you're right, good point. Yeah.
Yesterday wasn't it suggested that a small child kind of like should
go as long as he can walk with his father?
Right, so that's חינוך, chinuch, and we'll talk about that. But here
it's even טף, taf, like even infants. Okay, so even less than
that age.
Would you say it's a should or is it an obligation?
By the case of the children in the משנה, it's an obligation
but like a חינוך chinuch obligation. We'll talk about that when we
get to that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so that's how, although again, not פשט pshat in the משנה,
but because in order to fit in a ברייתא Braisa into the
משנה, we're arguing that even missing one of these faculties is exempt
from the מצוה mitzvah of הקהל, Hakhel.
of bringing a קרבן ראייה. korban re'iyah. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמר רבי תנחום, Amar Rabbi Tanchum, says רבי תנחום,
Rabbi Tanchum, חרש באוזן אחת פטור מן הראייה. cheresh b'ozen achas patur
min hare'iyah. So the same way we've exempted already blind in one
eye, and ממילא mimeila there talks about seeing, being seen, etc., now
based on this הקהל Hakhel. comparison, we've exempted deaf and now we're
going to even exempt more, and even deaf in one ear. Okay,
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the verse says, באזניהם, b'ozneihem, by הקהל, Hakhel? right?
You shall read this תורה Torah in their ears.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והאי באזניהם מיבעי ליה באזניהם דכולי ישראל.
v'hai b'ozneihem miba'i lei b'ozneihem d'chuli Yisrael. What do you mean? It
means the ears of all of the people, not each individual's two
ears.
All of them together have a lot of ears. So it doesn't
necessarily mean each person's two ears. So the גמרא Gemara says, no.
ההוא—what? hahu מנגד כל ישראל נפקא. mineged kol Yisrael nafka. No, no,
no. There it says read it opposite all of the people. So
you don't have to have the word in their ears unless you
wanted to indicate that they needed to have both ears functioning. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. אי מנגד כל ישראל הוה אמינא נפקא
דלא שמעי. ei mineged kol Yisrael hava amina nafka d'lo sham'ei. If
it just said read it in front of them, I would have
said that there's no obligation by הקהל Hakhel. to be in earshot.
Okay, I'm there, it's in front of me, again it's the
experiential thing. It's not necessarily hearing. So therefore כתב רחמנא באזניהם, kasav
rachmana b'ozneihem, it says read it in their ears, they have to
be able to be hearing it. But it still doesn't prove that
it means they have to be able to hear with both ears.
They have a lot of ears, all of the people. So, okay.
והוא דשמעי, v'hu d'sham'ei, yes, but etc., you have to be able
to hear it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. ההוא מלמען ישמעו
נפקא. hahu milma'an yishme'u nafka. If it just wanted to tell me
they had to hear, it already says read it to them in
order that they hear, למען ישמעו. So I have already figured out
that they have to hear. So why does it say באזניהם b'ozneihem
to tell you that each individual needs to have both ears to
be functioning? Okay, and now we've excluded even again from הקהל, which
is one thing which is about an experience of reading, not an
experience of seeing, but from הקהל we've excluded even deaf in one
ear and now we've applied that to עולת ראייה. אמר רבי תנחום,
Amar Rabbi Tanchum, now, חיגר ברגל אחת פטור מן הראייה. chiger b'regel
achas patur min hare'iyah. Are you noting a theme here? Somebody who
is lame in one leg, right, because it's עולת ראייה and you
have to be עולה לרגל oleh laregel and the משנה speaks about
אינו יכול לעלות, eino yachol la'alos, somebody who cannot. So let's say
somebody just is lame in one leg, okay? שנאמר, she-ne'emar, and basically
has like some type of a prosthesis or whatever in for that
leg, even that person is exempt. שנאמר רגלים. she-ne'emar regalim.
Okay, which is, and this is not, many assume that this is
not just a play on words, right? The reason it's called שלוש
רגלים בשנה, shalosh regalim bashanah, now רגל regel can mean like times,
right? Like when the donkey says to בלעם, Bilam, כי הכיתני זה
שלוש רגלים, ki hikisani zeh shalosh regalim, okay, but it also very
much could mean they are called three pilgrimage festivals, the רגל, regel,
they are the times when you travel. Okay? So since it says,
since it says רגלים, regalim, your legs, so you need both legs.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והא רגלים מיבעי ליה פרט לבעלי קבין?
ve-ha regalim miba'i lei prat le-ba'alei kabin? But one minute, what we
exclude from that—I'm sorry, I jumped ahead when I said prosthesis—we exclude
from that somebody who has a prosthesis. So even though maybe they
can walk around, since they don't have a רגל, regel, even though
they're mobile because of their prosthesis, they're excluded because they don't have
רגלים. regalim. So but not to exclude somebody who's just lame in
one leg. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. ההוא מפעמים נפקא. hahu
mipa'amim nafka. To exclude people that have a prosthesis but are mobile,
we exclude them not from the word of רגל regel which means
they need a leg, but from the word of פעמים pa'amim which
means times, but פעם pa'am doesn't just mean times, פעם pa'am also
means feet or like your
soles. Okay? דתניא, Detanya,
it taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, פעמים, pa'amim, right? שלוש פעמים בשנה,
shalosh pa'amim bashanah, so... אין פעמים אלא רגלים, ein pe'amim ela regalim,
פעמים pe'amim means not even legs, it means feet. וכן הוא אומר:
vechen hu omer: תרמסנה רגל, tirmesena regel, רגלי
עני פעמי דלים. raglei ani pa'amei dalim. It will be trampled by
the foot, the legs of the poor, the soles, the feet of
the
impoverished. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, and here's a clearer פסוק:
pasuk: מה יפו פעמיך בנעלים בת נדיב. ma yafu pa'amayich b'nealim bat
nadiv.
How beautiful are your feet in shoes, the daughter of the generous
one. But anyway, your feet are what are in the shoes. Okay,
so therefore there's a פעם pa'am means a foot. So it's quite
fascinating, right? שלוש רגלים shalosh regalim and שלוש פעמים, shalosh pe'amim, they
both derive from a word about leg and foot. So anyway, so
therefore somebody who has a prosthesis doesn't have a foot. So which
would be actually interesting, which would mean not only if the leg
is cut off, even if, you know, the person just has lost
his foot, even if he has his leg, that's being excluded. So
therefore what do you need, if that's excluded from פעמים, pe'amim, what
do you need רגלים regalim to exclude? From somebody who isn't physically
missing the leg but is just lame in one leg. And we
need רגלים regalim meaning you need both legs. And therefore even lame
in one leg is excluded. Again, you know, it's just I gotta
just tell you that it's like hard reading all this. Again, I
acknowledge that we're not excluding, we're exempting, but, you know, when exempting
has the force sometimes of excluding. Yeah, we only are interested in
these people, those are the ones that really have to come up,
not the others. And again, like, you know, just the whole perfection
aspect that is sort of going on here. Look, in general it's
a problem of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? The fact that
you don't want קרבנות עם מומים, korbanot im mumim, you don't want
כהנים עם מומים, kohanim im mumim, everything is gold and silver and
beautiful and so on. And there's this idea about like people's expectations
about what a, you know, what like a house of God looks
like, and it has to be beautiful and glorious and perfect and
all that. But then there's also a deeper religious message that about
all of these physical things are not meaningful, right?
So, anyway, it is troubling reading all of these exemptions which also
wind up having to some degree a force of exclusion. Yes.
In the ancient world, the having a physical defect was seen as
disqualifying for other, not just in what we were talking about there,
but in other societies. So for instance when a king was overthrown,
what was often done was they would cut off his nose, which
would permanently prohibit him from serving as a king anymore and of
course come back and overthrow the
overthrow. Fascinating. That lasted throughout most of
Byzantine.
What was that? Was that based on anything or was that just
like sort of intrinsically understood?
That seems to have been intrinsically understood,
like if you're deformed then you're פסול. pasul. Like, okay, interesting, right,
fascinating.
I mean obviously it sounds ridiculous. We had a president who couldn't
walk in this country.
Fascinating. Okay, right. All right so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Now
we're going to have a little אגדתא. agadata. דרש רבא: darash Rava:
מאי דכתיב, mai d'ichtiv, what's meant by the verse מה יפו פעמיך
בנעלים בת נדיב? ma yafu pa'amayich b'nealim bat nadiv? כמה נאים רגליהם
של ישראל, kama na'im ragleihem shel Yisrael, אגדתא agadata that is exactly
on topic, how beautiful are the legs of Israel. מה יפו פעמיך,
ma yafu pa'amayich, feet, legs, בשעה שעולים לרגל, beshaa sheolin l'regel, when
they go up to the רגל, regel, and how beautiful is it
that they're all coming and going up לרגל. l'regel. בת נדיב, bat
nadiv, what's the daughter of the generous one?
בתו של אברהם אבינו bito shel Avraham Avinu שנקרא נדיב, shenikra nadiv,
the daughter of Abraham who was called generous, שנאמר נדיבי עמים נאספו,
shene'emar nedivei amim ne'esafu, the generous ones of the nations should gather,
עם אלהי אברהם, am Elohei Avraham, the nation of the God of
Abraham, which is interesting because Abraham isn't the נדיב, nadiv, the נדיב
nadiv is the עמים, amim, but okay anyway it's in juxtaposition. So
אלהי אברהם Elohei Avraham ולא אלהי יצחק ויעקב? v'lo Elohei Yitzchak v'Yaakov?
What, why only the God of Abraham? Why aren't they gathering to
give recognition to the God of you know to the God of
Yitzchak and Yaakov? It's the same God, why is it only called
the God of Abraham? אלא
אלהי אברהם שהיה תחילה לגרים, ela Elohei Avraham shehaya techila lagerim, because
Abraham was the first of converts. Now what does it mean the
first of converts, right? So רש"י Rashi says, right, נדיבי עמים, nedivei
amim, רש"י Rashi says: הם הגרים המתנדבים מבין העמים, hem hagerim hamitnadvim
mibein ha'amim, the sort of ones that
are sort of you know give of themselves from the nations, לקבל
עליהם עול מצוות. lekabel aleihem ol mitzvot. So understand that this is
referring to converts and they're giving of themselves to accept the עול
מצוות, ol mitzvot, which therefore suggests that Abraham is the first of
those, for of those that listen to the sound of God. Right,
Abraham is the model, you know, there's different models for גרים, gerim,
אברהם, Avraham, רות, Rut, one is maybe more of a religious calling,
the other is identifying with the people. But this idea so if
we're talking about גרים, gerim, אברהם Avraham is the one that is
pulling, you know, he sort of led the way of giving of
himself to God. There's another way of understanding it, I mean first
of all תוספות Tosafot makes it more
technical: תחילה לגרים שנתחייב על המילה. techila lagerim shenitchayev al hamila. So
yes, and מילה mila obviously is the אות ot of the ברית,
brit, but anyway, רש״י Rashi I think is a little bit more
powerful, but the other way to think about it is also that
אברהם Avraham had a lot of followers, right? You know, he had
all these people following him and חז״ל Chazal make it like אברהם
Avraham was מגייר megayer men and שרה Sarah was מגייר megayer women,
נפש אשר עשו בחרן, nefesh asher asu b'Charan, etc. But even פשט
הפסוקים, pshat hapsukim, he called people to follow God. He was going
all around the place and saying, right, and saying,
you know, ויקרא בשם ה׳, Vayikra b'shem Hashem, ויקרא בשם ה׳, Vayikra
b'shem Hashem, you know, etc. So he was calling people and this
is about people being called to recognize God. So, and there's also
a very nice parallel because what is the רגל? regel? רגל regel
is people coming from all around, נדיבי עמים נאספו, nidvei amim ne'esafu,
and coming to the mountain of God, right? So I think, you
know, again, while רש״י Rashi reads it more as like about גרים
geirim and converts, I think that there's a power here about, you
know, about the event of the pilgrimage, like, you know, people notice
when everybody is doing a pilgrimage, you know, and it's a, and
that is like a sense of coming together to recognize and to
call to God. So there could be here a sense of like,
you know, of the calling of others and the impact that it
has on others as well. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, continues.
אמר רב כהנא דרש רב נתן בר מניומי משמיה דרבי תנחום. Amar
Rav Kahana darash Rav Natan bar Minyomi mishumei d'Rabbi Tanchum. Now, the
only reason we're having this דרשה drasha is because it was Rabbi
Tanchum that excluded deaf in one ear and lame in one leg,
so he has an aggadic statement in the name of Rabbi Tanchum.
מאי דכתיב, Mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the verse והבור ריק אין
בו מים? Vehabor reik ein bo mayim? Very famous דרשה drasha by
יוסף. Yosef. The pit was empty, there was no water.
מכדי שנאמר, Machshe ne'emar, והבור ריק איני יודע שאין בו מים? Vehabor
reik eini yode'a she'ein bo mayim? Of course there's no water. ריק
reik is empty. אלא מים אין בו. Ella mayim ein bo. No,
the point is it was only empty of water, אבל נחשים ועקרבים
יש בו, aval nechashim v'akravim yesh bo, snakes and scorpions there were
there, just to show how bad it was what the brothers did.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מעשה ברבי יוחנן בן ברוקא ורבי אלעזר
חסמא רבי אלעזר בן חסמא שהלכו להקביל פני רבי יהושע בפקיעין. Ma'aseh
b'Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka v'Rabbi Eleazar Chasma Rabbi Eleazar ben Chasma shehalchu
l'hakbil pnei Rabbi Yehoshua biPki'in. So they, these two Rabbis went to
visit Rabbi Yehoshua in פקיעין. Pki'in. Presumably it was יום טוב Yom
Tov or something, right? You know, where you're supposed to be עולה,
oleh, you're supposed to be מקביל פני רבו makbil pnei rabbo on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. אמר להם, Amar lahem, and he said to
them, מה חידוש היה בבית המדרש היום? Ma chiddush haya b'veit hamidrash
hayom? Oh, what, you know, what new thing came up in the
בית מדרש Beit Midrash today? אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to
him, תלמידיך אנו ממימיך אנו שותים. Talmidecha anu m'meimecha anu shotim. We're
your students, we drink from your waters, we have nothing to tell
you that, you know, that you wouldn't know. אמר להם, Amar lahem,
he said back to them, אף על פי כן, Af al pi
chen, אי אפשר לבית המדרש בלא חידוש. iy efshar l'veit hamidrash belo
chiddush.
It's impossible that there was a time in the study hall that
some new idea did not pop up and I can learn too,
so tell me what, tell me what, what came up.
שבת של מי היה? Shabas shemi haya? Whose week was it? Like
they would do a rotation of weeks and different people would sort
of be in the head position, you know, each week. Whose week
was it? So שבת Shabas and also particularly this relates to a
whole story about where there was a whole competition about who would
get to lead and the way basically
the פשרה pshara that they had is that they'd be on an
alternating rotation. Okay, there's a whole big story here about a whole
like major, you know, major
rivalry in terms of who would be able to lead. Okay, anyway,
so he asked, whose week was it? שבת דרבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Shabas d'Rabbi Eleazar ben Azarya. It was the week of רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה. Rabbi Eleazar ben Azarya. He was heading the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash. that week. It was his turn. ובמה הייתה הגדה היום?
Uvema hayta hagada hayom?
And what was the הגדה Hagada today? Which is fascinating, which makes
it sound like each day it was, I don't know, it would
start with, but there would be, there would be a teaching of
הגדה Hagada time together with a teaching of הלכה. Halacha. They wouldn't
be learning, you know, they, you know, maybe some of the Lithuanian
Yeshivas could learn something from that. It wouldn't just be all, all
learning
of הלכה Halacha and hard סוגיות. sugyot. You'd also open with a
little דברי השקפה. divrei hashkafa. So what was the הגדה Hagada today?
אמרו
לו, Amru lo, so they said to him, בפרשת הקהל. B'parshat Hakhel.
It was הקהל. They were learning about the פרשה Parsha of הקהל.
ומה דרש בה? Uma darash ba? So what did רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה Rabbi Eleazar ben Azarya have to say about הקהל? הקהל את
העם האנשים והנשים והטף. אם אנשים באים
ללמוד, Im anashim ba'im lilmod, so this obviously picking up on the
theme before about הקהל. The men we understand, they're coming to learn.
נשים באות לשמוע. Nashim ba'ot lishmo'a. Women, alright, they're hearing, they're maybe
not understanding what's being said, you know, again, you know, I'm not
assuming here that the גמרא assumed that women were any less intelligent,
but certainly they were less educated and, you know, maybe didn't even
know, you know, assumed not to know the language or certainly not
to understand, you know, have a depth of understanding. But again, I'm
assuming it's based on lack of education, not lack of intellect is
the גמרא's assumption. But anyway, so women are hearing at least. But
טף למה באים? taf lama ba'im? Why are the babies coming? Not
only can they not learn, you know, it's like, you know, it's
all gibberish to them. כדי ליתן שכר למביאיהם. Kedei litein sachar limvi'eihem.
Ah,
no,
the reason the infants are bringing is to give reward to those
that bring them. Which a little bit begs the question, right? Because
like, if they're not serving any purpose, why are you getting reward
for... bringing them, you know, so it's a little bit unclear, but
one, you know, could say first, you know, that the fact that
you are bringing them makes an impression upon you about the importance
of bringing your children and having your children present in these religious
types of experiences, right? So it has an, you know, you could
say it has even an impact on the kids, you know, even
if they're very small, you never know exactly, you know, if they're
a week old maybe, but if they're a year old or two
years old, you know, maybe there is some type of an impact
of, you know, some memory of some type of a powerful experience.
But here it's sort of talking also about the impact on you
to bring them and the importance of making sure that they are
present for these types of things that will have an impact on
your parenting. So אמר להם amar lahem he said to them, מרגלית
טובה הייתה בידכם וביקשתם לאבדם ממני, margalit tovah hayetah beyadchem u-vikashtem l'abdem
mimeni, you had this beautiful pearl in your
hands and you wanted to lose it, you know, waste it from
me, you wanted to, to deprive me of it, it was a
beautiful idea. So, you know, why did I have to sort of
pull it out of you? Okay, now by the way, there's two
interesting
תוספות, Tosafot, נשים לשמוע Nashim lishmo'a says תוספות, Tosafot, אמר בירושלמי דלא
כבן עזאי דאמר חייב אדם ללמד לבתו תורה, amar birushalami d'lo k'ben
azzai d'amar chayav adam lelamed l'vito torah, right? So there's a position
of בן עזאי Ben Azzai that an obligation to teach one's daughter
תורה, Torah, so the women would be educated and the women therefore
would also be coming in order not just to hear but also
to learn. And that would be an important value, not just they
would be able to learn but they would be necessary for them
to learn. So that's, you know, again, that comes up in סוטה
Sotah whatever, all these issues about education, you know, תורה Torah education
for women, important that תוספות Tosafot raises that position. Notice already now
two ירושלמי Yerushalmis that are being very inclusive. Number one is that
women have to be עולה לרגל oleh l'regel even if they don't
have to bring a קורבן, korban, and women are חייב to learn
תורה. Torah. כדי ליתן שכר למביאיהם, kedei litein sechar l'mevi'eihem, look at
the next תוספות, Tosafot, ועל זה סמכו להביא קטנים לבית הכנסת. v'al
zeh samchu lehavi k'tanim l'veit haknesset. Okay,
which is a whole important issue, right? Having children in the שול,
shul, does that ruin the decorum, does it make it hard for
other people to דאוון? daven? But what about the impact that it's
going to have on the children, and what about the impact it's
going to have on the parents of having their children there? So
very interesting, you know, issues that come up about that. Yes.
When can we start the ירושלמי Yerushalmi in English?
Okay, yes, Ben.
I think it's like, I think it must be the case that
in this story where they're going to visit him, it's not the
חג, chag, it's visiting him because he's infirm. He's too infirm to
come to the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash?
What makes you say that?
Because it would make the story so perfect. Okay. Because the whole
story is about
oh you can't come,
who gets brought when they can't come, is the מצער, m'tzar, and
they tell him oh you're our רבי, Rebbe, you're our teacher, we
learn from you. Why isn't he in the בית מדרש? Beit Midrash
Why wasn't he in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash. that day? Oh,
it actually can't be the חג, chag, right? It would be strange
if it's the חג chag and they're talking about...
Well, I was wondering that too, the assumption that it was a
normal בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. I mean, they would have learning on
the חג chag and the famous but but you know, but yes,
I mean,
the whole interaction why they don't want to tell him the תורה
Torah in the first place because it's embarrassing to tell him...
It's interesting. I appreciate that.
You kept me from learning because you're not bringing me to the
בית מדרש.
Beit Midrash Right, right, I appreciate that. That's very nice. יישר כוח,
Shkoach, יישר כוח. Shkoach. But they did have the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash on חג. chag. That's clear, like they have in the whole
אגדתא aggadeta in the beginning of the second פרק perek of ביצה
Beitzah there, like the רבי was דרשן darshening the whole day and
slowly the students were trickling out because they wanted to actually have
a סעודה seudah on יום טוב Yom Tov or whatever, and he
got angry at them. But they did have the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash, even on the חג. chag.
Small points from earlier. אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu had a daughter.
Yeah, yeah, did you know that? Did you know that? בכל Bakol
was her name.
בכל, Bakol, yeah.
No, anyway, just personifying the people as a, whatever, it's a metaphor.
אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא. amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu. Okay,
moving on. Okay, so you have this beautiful thing and you wanted
to deprive me of it, rob me of it. ועוד דרש, ve-od
darash, and then he also explicated, now who's the he? Presumably this
he is, what do you call it, is רבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. את ה' האמרת היום, et Hashem he'emarta hayom,
God you have chosen today. It's interesting what האמרת he'emarta means, רש"י
Rashi says you have elevated today, chosen today. וה' האמירך היום, v'Hashem
he'emircha hayom, and God has chosen you. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא
לישראל, amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu l'Yisrael, God said to the people
of Israel, אתם עשיתוני חטיבה אחת בעולם, atem asituni chativa achat ba-olam,
you have made me one like unit. It's also interesting what חטיבה
chativa means, but like one object, one thing, one unit in the
world. ואני אעשה אתכם חטיבה אחת בעולם, ve-ani e'eseh etchem chativa achat
ba-olam,
I will make you as רש"י Rashi says חטיבה chativa here means
a praise, but it seems a little more concrete to me, anyway,
one unit in the world. אתם עשיתוני חטיבה אחת בעולם דכתיב שמע
ישראל ה' אלוהינו ה' אחד, atem asituni chativa achat ba-olam d'chtiv Shma
Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem echad, we declare God as one. ואני אעשה
אתכם חטיבה אחת בעולם, ve-ani e'eseh etchem chativa achat ba-olam, I'll make
you as one, שנאמר shene'emar as the verse says, ומי כעמך ישראל
גוי אחד בארץ. u-mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba-aretz. I declare that
you are one. Okay. And again, the sense of one also is
like not only declaring that you're unique, but also there's an implicit
sense of declaring our chosen one, right? ה' אלוהינו, Hashem Elokeinu, right?
ומי כעמך ישראל, u-mi k'amcha Yisrael, you know, there's a sense also
about, you know, about God sort of when you, you know, sort
of acknowledging the uniqueness but also therefore a sense of the relationship
and the chosenness of them. Because it is interesting the shift, the
פסוק pasuk talks about, you know, about you sort of like, you
know, again, what האמרת he'emarta means, but there is that sense of,
you know, choosing God and God choosing you. And here talking more
about declaring the uniqueness, which is important, but it loses a little
bit of the flavor of choosing. But I think that they're not
exclusive. Okay. So anyway, now, by the way, there's an interesting תוספות
Tosafot here also, we'll read very quickly: ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד
בארץ, Umi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz, ומן המדרש שלושה מעידים זה
על זה, Umin hamidrash shlosha mei'idim zeh al zeh,
three things testify on one another: ישראל ושבת והקדוש ברוך הוא. Yisrael
v'Shabbat v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu. ישראל והקדוש ברוך הוא מעידים על השבת שהוא
יום מנוחה, Yisrael v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu mei'idim al haShabbat she'hu yom menucha,
right, the Jews by observing it and God by making it a
שבת. Shabbat. ישראל ושבת על הקדוש ברוך הוא, Yisrael v'Shabbat al Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, Jews and שבת Shabbat sort of, you know, sort of
testify on God, you know, and again שהוא אחד, she'hu echad, he's
one, right? Because again the שבת Shabbat is about God as creator
and so on and the Jewish people both by observing שבת Shabbat
and generally by their whole existence and their relationship to God. הקדוש
ברוך הוא ושבת על ישראל שהם יחידים באומות, Hakadosh Baruch Hu v'Shabbat
al Yisrael she'hem yechidim be'umot, and God and the שבת Shabbat on
ישראל, Yisrael. God because the unique relationship God has and שבת Shabbat
because it sets us apart and the uniqueness of ישראל. ועל זה
סמכינו לומר אתה אחד במנחה בשבת, Ve'al zeh samchinu lomar Ata Echad
b'Mincha b'Shabbat, right? אתה אחד ושמך אחד Ata Echad ve'shimcha echad is
how we sort of begin the מנחה, Mincha, the middle section in
the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. What does it have to do with
שבת? Shabbos? אף על פי שאינו מדבר עניינא דיומא דשבת Af al
pi she'einu medaber inyana d'yoma d'Shabbos כתפילות מעריב ושחרית, ke'tefillot Maariv v'Shacharis,
it doesn't immediately get into the שבת Shabbat idea, right, as we
do by שחרית Shachris and מעריב, Maariv, but nevertheless there's this whole
idea of אחד echad which is about God and שבת Shabbat and
ישראל. So that's an interesting like little השלמה hashalama to this
דרשה. drasha. Okay. Now ואף הוא פתח ודרש, ve'af hu patach v'darash,
even he, who's the even he? So רש"י Rashi says it's still
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah, just saying oh he
had a third דרשה. drasha. But others say that now we're shifting
to who was it that they were visiting? רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
all right, who was רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar like peer, so they're
shifting to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So אלעזר Elazar they told him
these nice ideas רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah had,
and now רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua gonna say a דרשה. drasha. ואף
הוא פתח ואמר, ve'af hu patach v'amar, so now he said back
to them the following דרשה drasha ודרש: v'darash: דברי חכמים כדורבנות וכמסמרות
נטועים בעלי אסופות ניתנו מרועה אחד. Divrei chachamim kadorbanot uchmasmerot netuim ba'alei
asufot nitnu mei'ro'eh echad. The words of sages are like prods, like
nails sort of stuck into, you know, prodding sticks. There's a question
what בעלי אסופות ba'alei asufot means; the JPS translation says meaning of
Hebrew uncertain. Okay, anyway, they have all been given from one shepherd.
So למה נמשלו דברי תורה לדורבן, lama nimshelu divrei Torah ladorban, why
are words of תורה Torah similar to like a prodding stick? לומר
לך מה דורבן זה מכוון את הפרה לתלמיה, Lomar lecha mah dorban
zeh mechavein et haparah letalmeha, the same way a prodding stick directs
the cow, you know, to its furrow, keeps the cow in line,
להוציא חיים לעולם, lehotzi chayim la'olam, and what do you do by
plowing land? You know, life comes out of the ground, right, plants,
growth, it brings forth life. אף דברי תורה מכוונים את לומדיהם מדרכי
מיתה לדרכי חיים. Af divrei Torah mechavnim et lomdeihem midarchei mita ledarchei
chayim. So the words of תורה, Torah, you know, they're like constraining,
they're prodding you, you have to walk in a straight line, you
walk a narrow line, but ultimately it brings forth
life, okay, and it directs them from the path of death to
the path of life.
Does it remember fertilizer? No, let's tell that one.
The furrow. So the cow plows. Oh, so you're keeping the cow
in line to do the plowing and make the furrow, and that
therefore brings out the thing. You're keeping the people in line to
walk the,
you know, to walk the, you know, the tightrope, but ultimately that
leads to a life of true life.
That's what the prod does.
The prod keeps you in line.
Not a pasture?
No, you're keeping him to walk a straight line. Cows have to
walk a straight line to make a straight furrow and we have
to walk a straight line ultimately to lead to a life
of life.
To say and another דרשות drashot the עול, ol, like the עול.
ol.
Well, עול ol is more restrictive. Okay, right. Okay, right. But this
is even more, I think, you know, clearly keep you going in
a straight line.
Is there a connection between דורבן darban and דרבנן? d'rabbanan?
Oh, that's cute, maybe. אם מה דורבן זה מטלטל אף דברי תורה
מטלטלים? Im mah dorban zeh metalal af divrei Torah metalalim? Maybe the
same way that a prod is, you know, sort of movable, so
words of תורה Torah can, you know, be moved around. Now what
does that mean? You can move around, you go and you talk
to whoever you want, but presumably the point here being about the
importance of putting yourself in one place, you know, and not traveling
all around. If you want to really succeed in תורה Torah you
have to set down roots. So
תלמוד לומר מסמרות, talmud lomar masmerot, like a, you know, a peg
or like a nail which is something in a fixed place. Now
obviously in the image in the פסוק pasuk it's a nail in
a, like in a, you know, in a stick which you lead,
you know, you use to actually, it's a serious prod. But okay.
אם מה מסמר זה חסר ולא יתר אף דברי תורה חסרים ולא
יתרים? Im mah masmer zeh chaseir velo yateir af divrei Torah chaseirim
velo yeteirim? Okay, but a nail like, okay, it gets, it can
lose, you know, it can rust, it can get, it can get
taken away from but it certainly doesn't increase, it's very static, if
anything it just, you know, gets worse. So maybe the same about
תורה? Torah? תלמוד לומר נטועים. talmud lomar netuim. no, planted. מה נטיעה
זו פרה ורבה, ma netiah zu parah ve-rabah, the same way a
planting is fruitful and multiplies, אף דברי תורה פרים ורבים, af divrei
torah parim ve-rabim, so Torah also is fruitful and multiplies, so it
brings forth fruit
and it leads to other people, it spreads and so on, which
maybe also is the idea of staying fixed in one place. If
you fixed in one place, it'll have an impact and it'll bring
forth other people to engage in it and so on. בעלי אסופות
baalei asufot and now we're going to get to the communal aspect
of Torah, which is again part of this being fixed in one
place and the פרה ורבה. parah ve-rabah. So בעלי, baalei,
masters of אסופות, asufot, again, so might be like collections, whatever this
means. אלו תלמידי חכמים שיושבין אסופות אסופות, eilu talmidei chachamim she-yoshvin asufot
asufot, this is the idea of having a big בית מדרש, Beis
Medrash, right? Torah sages that are gathered, like in groups and groups,
ועוסקים בתורה, ve-oskim ba-torah, and they learn Torah all together. הללו
מטמאין והללו מטהרין, hallalu metamin ve-hallalu metaherin, but now of course there's
a little bit of a problem. You have multiple voices. These people
say טמא, tamei, those say טהור. tahor. הללו אוסרין והללו מתירין, hallalu
osrin ve-hallalu mattirin, these people say אסור, assur, those say מותר. muttar.
הללו פוסלין והללו מכשירין, hallalu poslin ve-hallalu machshirin, these people invalid, these
say valid. So you get all these different voices. Now, in a
way that's beautiful. That's the energy of the Torah, what makes it
alive. But and that's the beautiful thing, just like the פרה ורבה,
parah ve-rabah, the sense of the being fruitful and having all of
this diversity. But שמא יאמר אדם היכא אני לומד תורה מעתה, shema
yomar adam heicha ani lomed torah me-atah, but how am I supposed
to figure my way? There's too many different voices. How am I
supposed to—right, if I don't have one message? תלמוד לומר כולם נתנו
מרועה אחד, talmud lomar kullam nittnu me-roeh echad, the end of it
says they're all being given from one shepherd. אל אחד נתנן פרנס
אחד אמרן, el echad netanan parnas echad amran, one God has given
them, one sustainer has said them, מפי אדון כל המעשים ברוך הוא.
mi-pi adon kol ha-maasim baruch hu. It's all comes from the mouth
of the Master of all Creation, דכתיב וידבר אלוהים את כל הדברים
האלה. de-chtiv va-yedabber elohim et kol ha-devarim ha-eileh. All of these things.
So all of the different voices all come from God. So אף
אתה עשה אזנך כאפרכסת, af attah aseh oznecha ke-afarkeset, make your ear
like a funnel, take it all in. וקנה לך לב מבין לשמוע
את דברי מטמאים ואת דברי מטהרים. u-knei lecha lev mevin lishmoa et
divrei metameim ve-et divrei metaherim. It's such a beautiful image here. וקנה
לך לב מבין u-knei lecha לב מבין to hear את דברי מטמאים
ואת דברי מטהרים—you et divrei metameim ve-et divrei metaherim have a responsibility,
it's not just about absorbing and spitting back. You have to work
to gain a discerning heart, to develop your judgment and your intellect
and your analytic ability to be able to hear but also to
discern the different arguments, those that say טמא, tamei, את דברי אוסרים
ואת דברי מתירים, et divrei osrim ve-et divrei mattirim, את דברי פוסלים
ואת דברי מכשירים, et divrei poslim ve-et divrei machshirin, to hear all
those different voices
and to hear them in a discerning way. And that then becomes
your responsibility to navigate your way with all of those different voices.
So it's quite fascinating. On the one hand, you have the idea
of walking a narrow path, which is very like keep your eyes
in front of you, it's all very well defined. And then you
have this very fructifying, fruitful and multiply and spreading out and all
these voices, like which way do I go? And then it sort
of speaks about like, your responsibility is to find that path and
to find the sort of way within all of that. But that's
also the beauty of Torah. Going back to Ben's point also about
the context here, here he is, he's talking about the importance of
being in a lively בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, and he wasn't in
the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, and he said אין בית המדרש בלא
חידוש, ein beit ha-midrash belo chiddush, which also to some degree means,
like, there's a lot of different voices. You would hear voices that
aren't my voices. I want to hear those voices. And even if
so, there's this also beauty of acknowledging like it's not all coming
from, even if all my Torah. And there's what to be learned
from all of the different voices. It plays out very nicely at
the beginning of the story. Yes.
Although in this context of excluding people for various specific reasons, which
special years they wouldn't want to adopt some of the intellectual or
Torah differences we wanted to talk about now.
Yeah, but you don't hear any emphasis about any—I mean, I'm not
disagreeing with that, but I don't hear any allusion to this question
about physical disabilities or
including—you're hearing different voices. You're not opening it to different people, but
you're hearing multiple voices. I'm not disagreeing, I think that comes up
other places, I just don't hear it here. Okay, now let's try
to get one more story in like this.
בלשון הזה אמר להם bi-lashon ha-zeh amar lahem and in this language
he said to them, this is how we conclude what he says.
אין דור יתום שרבי אלעזר בן עזריה שרוי בתוכו. ein dor yatom
she-rabbi elazar ben azaryah sharui be-tocho. So there is no orphan generation
that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah is there. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was running the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash? you heard great Torah, and there is again, it's interesting,
what the—I'm not sure how that imagery applies in, orphan and so
on. Anyway, but it was great that you heard this Torah from
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. Also רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah talked about—did talk about parents and children
and about bringing the טף taph in order that they
would—כדי שיתנו שכר למביאיהם kedei she-yitnu sachar le-mevi-eihem and that's also this
sort of sense of like, all this more inclusive sense. Anyway. Okay.
So now the גמרא says like this, ולימרו ליה בהדיא, ve-limru leih
be-hedya, so why did they have to go through
this little play—this little sort of like back and forth where it
says, oh, you are our רבי, we don't have anything to teach
you? No. אין
בית מדרש בלא חידוש, Ein Beis Medrash Belo Chidush, he asks what
came up in the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? So tell him. Okay,
why do you have to go through this little dance? So משום
מעשה שהיה Mishum Maaseh Shehaya because of another story in which they
didn't go through this dance and it did not end well.
Okay, דתניא, ותנא בברייתא, Utna Bevraisa, מעשה ברבי יוסי בן דורמסקית, Maaseh
Berebbi Yose Ben Durmaski, הלך להקביל פני רבי אליעזר בלוד. Halach Lehakbil
Pnei Rebbi Eliezer Belod. רבי אליעזר בן דורמסקית Rebbi Eliezer Ben Durmaski
went to receive רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer in לוד, Lod, and again
this maybe this might be where רש"י Rashi said before that it
was יום טוב Yom Tov because this particularly in the context in
which this appears seems to be very much being visiting רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer on יום טוב Yom Tov was a whole issue that
comes up in סוכה, Sukkah, and also להקביל פני Lehakbil Pnei might
have that sense. Anyway, ואמרו לו Veamru Lo they said to him,
he said to them, or he said to him, רבי יוסי בן
דורמסקית Rebbi Yose Ben Durmaskis that came to visit him, מה חידוש
היה בבית המדרש היום? Ma Chidush Haya Beveis Hamidrash Hayom? What new
idea came up in the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash, So he didn't
go through the dance. He didn't say, oh, I can't learn any,
you're my רבי, there's nothing to tell you. He gave him an
answer. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, נמנו וגמרו, Nimnu Vegamru, they took a
vote and they concluded, עמון ומואב מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית, Amon Umoav
Maasrin Maaser Ani Beshviis, that עמון Amon and מואב Moav which are
the lands, Transjordan lands, which were presumably settled by
Jews and they gave תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos Umaasros, they don't have, they
don't practice שמיטה, Shmita, they actually plow the land and plant the
land and do it on שמיטה, Shmita, and they give the tithes
that they give, the second tithe is not מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon
but מעשר עני Maaser Ani because מעשר עני Maaser Ani goes to
the poor. Okay, so אמר ליה, Amar Lei, which is very bizarre,
they're giving מעשר Maaser but they're not observing שמיטה. Shmita. אמר ליה,
Amar Lei, he said to him, יוסי, Yose, פשוט עיניך וקבל עיניך,
Pshot Eynecha Vekabel Eynecha,
stick out your hands and be ready to catch your eyes. פשט
ידיו וקבל עיניו, Pashat Yadav Vekibel Eynav,
he stuck out his hands and his eyes fell out of their
sockets. Okay, now why was he upset? Let's take a look. בכה
רבי אליעזר, Bacha Rebbi Eliezer, so רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer cried, ואמר,
Vaamar, סוד ה' ליראיו ובריתו להודיעם, Sod Hashem Liyereiav Uvriso Lehodiam, God's
secret is to those that fear him and his covenant to
inform them. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, לך אמור להם, Lech Emor Lahem,
go say to the people in the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash אל
תחושו למניינכם, Al Techoshu Leminyanechem, and do not be concerned about your
vote, which might mean like רש"י Rashi says don't be concerned that
maybe you got it wrong, but I think רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer
real point here is like, who needed your vote? We already knew
this. כך מקובלני מרבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Kach Mekublani Merebbi Yochanan Ben
Zakkai, I have a tradition from רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rebbi Yochanan
Ben Zakkai ששמע מרבו ורבו מרבו Sheshama Merabbo Verabbo Merabbo going all
the way back to הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, that עמון ומואב מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית, Amon
Umoav Maasrin Maaser Ani Beshviis, exactly what you said. So presumably he
was upset and that's also presumably why he quoted the פסוק Pasuk
of סוד ה' ליראיו Sod Hashem Liyereiav which is, I knew this,
and I was in a unique position, I had this as a
tradition. Who needs your vote? Who needs you to figure out should
we or shouldn't we have a debate or whatever? You should ask
the person who knows. I have this, I know this information, I
have a tradition all the way back to משה מסיני. Moshe Misinai.
As opposed to חידוש, Chidush,
as opposed to חידוש, Chidush, thank you, as opposed to חידוש. Chidush.
That's a חידוש? Chidush? That's a חידוש? Chidush? I have that information!
And it's just it's transmitted without any שקלא וטריא. Shakla Vetarya.
Right. And it should be noted that רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is
the one who rejects the idea of חידוש, Chidush, which is interesting,
therefore they ask the question מה חידוש, Ma Chidush, for רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer the key is מסורה. Mesora. What do you have? You
just say over what you've received from your רבי, you're not מחדש,
Mechadesh, it's all מסורה. Mesora. Right? So he got very upset that
they innovated this. No, it's a מסורה. Mesora. Now by the way
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai here is used loosely because this
is דרבנן. Derabbanan. The whole idea that they give a מעשר עני
Maaser Ani and they don't do שמיטה Shmita whatever clearly as we're
going to see that's all rabbinic. So this is a loose use
of the word הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai and my גמרא,
I don't know if yours on the left hand, ח"ל Chalam they
even say it. כלומר דבר ברור כהלכה למשה מסיני, Klomar Davar Barur
Kehalacha Lemoshe Misinai, and of course the ראש Rosh that points out
that this clearly is used metaphorically. So if they would have acknowledged
you, רבי, we have nothing to tell you, no חידוש, Chidush, you're
our entire source of knowledge and so on, so then even if
they would have got around to telling him this, they've already acknowledged
that ultimately he was the, you know, he was the transmitter and
it came from him. And that by the way it's ironic, right?
It's always like, you know, you're doing the wrong, you know, you're
getting it right for the wrong person. Like
presumably with רבי יהושע, Rebbi Yehoshua, he, he did not need them
to go through that dance. He's very happy for there to be
multiple voices. אין בית מדרש בלא חידוש. Ein Beis Medrash Belo Chidush.
He describes the בית מדרש where you have all these different voices.
I don't need to be the source. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer who
was the one who needed to be the, you know, transmitter of
מסורה, Mesora, for him they didn't say what they needed to. It
wasn't the same people, but you know, it's always the way it
is, right? You do, you make your correction, and then you do
it in cases where it wasn't necessary. So רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
had one particular view and he needed straight to to acknowledge that
he was the בעל המסורה Baal Hamesora and רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua
had a very different view and would have been happy to have
heard the multiple voices. Yes.
Weren't רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer the disputants
over the oven that ended up,
well that was exactly it and the exact problem was רבי אליעזר,
Rebbi Eliezer, thank you for pulling that together, right, the exact problem
of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was that he could, you know, he
could not accept a vote. That was against his מסורה *masorah*. So
that is exactly and then רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* is all that
no, we debate it, we hear multiple voices, we vote it, that's
תורה *Torah*. So it's exactly these two stories are like perfect in
demonstrating exactly that and exactly you have to what you should say
in response to מה חידוש חידש בבית המדרש היום *ma chiddush chiddesh
beveis hamedrash hayom*. Okay, so we will continue to unpack this last
idea of עמון ומואב *Ammon uMoav* tomorrow, but it's a perfect place
to end here
and at the תנא שלח נא *tanna shelach na* that that call
is the singular voice.